Just about every app that we ever use
today has a search function, right? So
today I want to show you how I go about
designing and implementing a search
feature in every Rails application that
I build. You know, this week I'm
actually building out the docs site for
instrumental components, my components
library for Ruby on Rails. And sure
enough, I needed a search component. So
I designed a search function, built it
into my Rails app with the help of
cursor of course, and then just like I
do with every UI component I build these
days, I extract it out into a component
that I can use again and users of my
instrumental components library can use
as well. So let's get into it. Here is
an example application that I just spun
up. Uh I created a model called posts.
Of course, I used the instrumental
scaffolding uh component for that. Very
straightforward. Every post has a title.
um and uh time that it was created. I
can go in and I can see the content. I
can edit the content in this form. Okay.
So, so far I've added four posts and I
can click this icon to launch my search
or I can use the keyboard shortcut for
forward slash to launch the search
function. Um most users expect that
these days and of course you should be
able to hit the escape key to close it
out. So I like to put the search in its
own modal popup uh right in the middle
of the screen. So then the user can just
start typing and you know this field is
autofocused by default. The user doesn't
have to like click again. So I can just
you know start typing the title of a
post or any content in the excerpt or
the content of the post to pull up the
results and then I can use the keyboard
up and down and I can just hit return to
go to that post. Um or of course I could
use the mouse as well. Let's see. So,
uh, this this post has the word, um,
clutch in it. So, I'll I'll just copy
that and I will, uh, actually search for
that. So, I pasted in clutch and it
brought up this post. So, as you can
see, the search query is going to find a
match if it's in the title or in the
excerpt field or in the body content.
And I was able to configure, you know,
which columns and which associated
records, like the rich text record
that's associated with posts, um, which
of those things are actually searchable.
And one more little detail here. So, if
I go into a form and when I'm in a form
and one of the fields is is focused, I
don't actually want to launch the modal
if I type the key forward slash. I want
that to actually be part of whatever I'm
typing in. It's really annoying if I if
I'm trying to type into a field and I
hit a key that would trigger a launch of
a modal or something. So, the stimulusJS
controller that I'm using, which I'll
show you in a second, to launch the
modal is smart enough to know if any
field on the current page is currently
focused. And if I defocus it and then I
hit the the slash key, then it actually
does launch the uh the modal. So, that's
pretty cool. Okay, so that is the search
function. Let me tear it out of this
application and I'll regenerate it. I'll
reinstall it and I'll show you all the
pieces and how to actually install it in
your Rails application. Um, especially
if you're using uh instrumental
components, which makes it super easy.
Okay, so off camera I just ripped it all
out and now I'm going to reinstall my
search component into this Rails app. As
you can see, uh, we no longer have the
search icon up here. We'll add that back
in just a minute. And if I hit the slash
key, nothing happens. It's not launching
anything. It's not even in the app.
Okay. So, let's go ahead and uh go into
our codebase and I'm going to run uh the
instrumental command for installing the
search component. So, I'm going to do
rails g instrumental
search. And you can check out my other
videos on how to actually install
instrumental components. And you can get
a license of course at
instrumental.dev. So, this this one is
about to install the search component.
And it's showing me an overview before I
install it. It also works with a couple
of other components that it'll pull in.
So that's all good to go. I'm going to
hit return to proceed with the
installation. Okay, so now this this
feature this search function needs a few
pieces of information in order to wire
it up, right? So the first thing that
it's going to ask me is what's the name
of the of the class that we're going to
be searching. So in this case, I want my
search feature to search for posts. So
I'm going to actually type in
post. Okay. So now we need to set up the
link that each search result is going to
point to. And in this case that would be
the posts show view. So typically it'll
be the show view for whatever class or
whatever model you are searching. Now,
the way that uh we're going to need to
wire this up and the way that the
generator is going to do that for us,
it's actually instructing me that um
leave out the uh the parenthesis part of
the path helper, right? So, normally the
the path helper to go to my posts path
would be post path with the uh the post
ID or the post slug in the URLs. That
that's just how my routes are set up.
Um, but in this case, we just want to
include the part without the
parenthesis. So, we'll do post path. I
know that's a little bit confusing.
That's just how the instrumental
generator works. Then afterward, we can
go in and inspect it and and tweak it if
we need to. Okay. So, next we need to
select the set of searchable columns on
the posts table that we'll want to
search the content for. So, um, first of
course, we want to search the titles of
posts. So, we'll select the title. And
yes, I want to add another column. Uh,
next we want to select the excerpt
column. And I'm done adding searchable
columns for now. Um, but you'll remember
that we're also searching the content of
posts. Now, that's not actually one of
the columns on the actual posts database
table because the content of the post is
a rich text field which uses the action
text uh, you know, column in the
database. So that's what we call an
associated record with posts. So in this
case it's asking me would I like to add
any associated records to search by and
in this case I do. And then it's going
to ask is that associated record a rich
text field because we sort of need to
treat that a little bit uh differently
when we build out the code. Uh so yes it
is. And what's the name of that rich
text field? So I can take a look at my
post model and I have this has rich text
um field here which I'm calling content.
That's like the content of the post,
right? So I'm going to say the name of
that rich text field is
content. And you know I I could add
other associations like for example if I
have like tags or categories and I want
to include the names of those tags or
categories um in the searchable content.
In this case I don't. We're keeping it
simple. So, I'm done adding uh
associated records to search by. Just a
couple more questions for me here. So,
when I get the search results, uh each
result is going to be a link to a post
and each of those search result is going
to have a title. So, it's asking me
which column on the post table do we
want to actually use as the title. And
of course, we want to use the post title
column. So, I'm going to select that.
And then the other thing if you remember
underneath each title I'm displaying
like a descriptive text. Um in this case
I do want to des uh I do want to show
that and we're going to use that excerpt
text. Okay. So it got all the
information that it needed and now uh
the component is being fully installed
and now it's all done. So uh I've
installed the component. Instrumental
components tells me that uh six files
have been added. We're going to take a
look at those in just a second. So um it
did add my stimulus controller which
handles all the JavaScript for this
search feature. It added a new service
object called search service. Added a
couple partials to build out the actual
search modal and the search results. And
then we have a search controller and
we're doing a little bit of uh of turbo
responses here as well. We did add one
new route to our routes file for uh
processing the search and uh there we
go. Okay. So um that is all set. Now,
let's see if it just works right out of
the box. I'm going to run bend dev to
restart my server. And I'll refresh my
page. And you'll notice I don't have the
icon here. And if I hit the the keyboard
shortcut for slash, it's not actually
launching anything. So, why isn't it
working? Well, there's one more step
that we need to do to get this fully
working. And that's to actually install
the search component in our layout where
we're going to have the search uh
available.
you know that this this last step is not
actually part of the generator because
your layout in each project may vary. So
let me show you how to um finish up this
implementation and then we'll look at
all the code that's involved here. All
right. So I'm going to go into my
application layout. Uh that's the layout
that is powering this page and all the
other pages that I'm currently working
with. So I'm going to go to the body tag
on that layout. And the first thing is I
want to add the stimulus controller to
the body tag. Now, the body tag might
already have a data controller. If it
does, then you'll want to add a second
one by adding a space. If it doesn't,
then you'll want to add a data
controller to your body tag. And the
stimulus controller that was installed
is in JavaScript controllers inside
components. That's where all of uh
instrumentals stimulus controllers uh
get installed. We added search
controller under here. So um since it is
namespaced under components we'll do
components dash dash
search. Okay. So then the other thing we
need to wire up here is the keyboard
shortcut. Right. So um in order for that
to work, we're going to need to add data
action because my body tag doesn't yet
have any uh data actions. And it's it
actually uh remembered that from when I
worked with it earlier. So on the key
down event, we want to use the component
search controller and we're going to
call keyboard launch. That is the method
that handles uh launching of the uh of
the modal. So let's try this out now.
And I'm going to refresh. And you'll
still notice that nothing is happening.
Why is that? Well, there's one more
piece that we need to do. And that is to
actually render the search uh partial.
So in if we go into
views the uh search component added this
search folder and this search partial
that that handles the actual modal popup
that that pops up. We need to include
that or render that out in uh the
layout. So that should work. Let's uh
just restart the server. I have a
shortcut for that. I'm going to refresh
here. And there we go. So now this modal
exists in the layout and we were able to
call it using the keyboard shortcut. Now
you'll notice that I don't have the icon
in the top of my of my layout here. So
let me show you how to add that piece.
So I want to add it right here. And this
whole top section is handled in the top
uh partial. And all of this is
documented in the instrumental
components documentation at at
instrumental.dev. So um you can follow
along there but I just wanted to
demonstrate it here in this video. So uh
this partial is handling basically this
whole block right here. And I want to
find this area and that is right here.
And so it actually already is set up for
for flex items. So I can add like an
additional item right here. And you'll
actually have this uh cut and paste uh
snippet provided to you in the docs. So
I just added this. This is just a div um
with some T1 CSS classes. And then uh
inside it we are rendering the search
icon and that is um powered by our icons
helper which comes with uh instrumental
components which then you know brings in
uh lucide icons. So the search icon is
there. We've got this div and you'll
also notice that we have data action and
that's a click event so that we can
actually click that icon and that's
going to call our components search
launch method. So, let's uh refresh
that. And there's our search icon. And
if I click it, it launches our search.
So, we're good to go. And then, of
course, uh it should work. Oops, I hit
escape to It's just a habit of hitting
escape there. Uh post. And I can use the
arrow keys to go up and down. Okay. So,
let's take let's unpack the actual code
that powers all of this. Um I'm not
doing anything fancy with this search
implementation. I'm not using an outside
service. So I'm not using any special
gems. All I'm using is a Postgress
database and some functionality that you
get for free with Ruby and Rails and
Postgress. It's super simple. Um great
for a a starter application. You can
really go a pretty far way with just a
simple implementation like this. So um
let's start from the front and then
we'll work our way to the back end. So
on the front end, I already showed you
kind of the markup. We're going to get
into the actual stimulus uh stimulusJS
controller. All that action is happening
in search controller JS. So we've got a
couple of targets uh the search modal
the input field and then the results. Um
we've got the launch method which is
called uh in two ways. One is using the
keyboard launch and that is triggered uh
when we you know hit the the slash key.
Um, and this is only going to work if
it's the slash key. And then this is
that special code that's checking for
whether um a any field on the page is
currently focused. And if it is, then it
would be considered is editable and we
are not going to actually launch because
we don't want to disrupt the typing into
a into a form. Right? So that's handled
there.
Um, this launch action is is hit
directly when we uh when we
click that search icon. You can see s um
launch. We're hitting that there. Okay.
So, uh moving down uh we have the close
functionality which which can be done a
few different ways. You can escape it
just by hitting the escape button and
that will close or you can click outside
and hide. So, let's take a look at the
actual uh search partial. So this gets a
little bit complex but we are adding
some data attributes on the actual
search modal. So um if I go like that
and we inspect this let me open this up.
We inspect the actual
modal you can see uh where is it? Um
this is the the main container which
actually goes around the whole page and
that's where you can see data action
click um click outside and hide and what
that does as you can see
if if I have it open and if I click
outside of it then it's going to hide.
So that's one really common UX thing
that we want to make sure that we have.
So I'm going to look at the search
controller again. Click outside and
hide. That's looking for the click
event. Then it's going to check if that
click event is inside of the actual
search modal box. So let me show you
that one more time. If I click in here,
anywhere in this white box, it's not
going to close it. But as soon as I
click just outside of it, it is going to
close it. And that's exactly what we
want. Um, next thing is the
um keyboard close. And that's looking
for the escape key event. So only this
will only fire if the escape key is is
hit and only if the search modal is
already open and if it is then it's
going to close it. So this close and
then we close and then we reset. So we
have a reset function down here which
will um hide the modal target. It'll
reset the input field back to empty,
right? because you don't want it to to
be like, you know, test and then um and
then close it and then reopen it and it
still says test. We want it to be fully
reset, right? So, uh that's what that
does. Um and then it also clears out uh
the results. Okay, so now now we start
to get into the interesting stuff, the
actual searching, right? So when I start
to type, every time I type in any
letter, it's going to hit my server
again to check for um search results.
And so that search action is happening
on the search input
field. So here is the text field and
that's wrapped in our wrapper which
comes with instrumental components which
you know styles up search field or
styles up any form field um like that.
Okay. Okay. So, here's the the text
field. We've got some, you know, it is
autofocused uh by default. And then
we've got this data attribute here. Um
it is the input target. And then the
action is
search. So anytime, so the event here is
input. So anytime I'm inputting into the
field, it's going to hit that which then
um does this this fetch fetch query
which is actually hitting my search
route. So let's go to my routes and that
is hitting this and that takes me to my
search
controller rails controller. That's the
search action. Look how simple this is.
It's just a few lines of code. Of
course, it there there's a bit more once
we dig into the search service, but
right here in the controller, um we are
calling the search service. I'll I'll
look at that in a second. Uh but we're
passing to it the model that we're
searching for. In this case, posts. And
then these are the two columns on posts
that we're going to search for. And then
we have these searchable associations
for rich text content. So you can you
can see now how the instrumental
component generator asked me for each of
these things. you know, the the class
name, the column names, the rich text,
the associated rich text. It pulled what
it asked me for, and it automatically
generated and inserted those values
right into this controller. Did that for
me right when I installed it. So, that's
the kind of, you know, kind of power
that you get when you're using
instrumental components. It just sort of
builds these files for you. And then, of
course, I can come in here and I can
tweak things if I need to. All right,
let's keep going a little bit.
Essentially, that is going to give us
some results and then we're going to
kind of process and display those
results using a turbo response. I'll get
to that in a second. Let's go into that
search
service. And we have a bit more
documentation right here inside the the
codes. It explains what it's expecting
to to receive. So we want the record
class. We want those searchable columns.
Then optionally any um associated uh
columns. Here is the code where we're
actually uh running the I like query. Um
and this is one of those features that
comes with Postgress databases. So this
this system actually will only work if
you're using a Postgress database. It's
not going to work with SQLite um or
MySQL. Um uh so uh we are going to
search first in those direct columns and
then we're going to search in the
associated columns and then it's going
to sort of combine all of those
conditions, join them together and then
that sort of builds out the results and
we return the results. Going back to our
controller, we receive those results.
Then we go to the turbo stream response
and we're going to go into our
views and you'll see search.turbo
stream and then this is going to find
the search results ID. So if we look at
the uh search partial it's going to find
this div which appears to be empty,
right? But this turbo stream update is
going to fill it with search results if
there are any. And if there's not then
it's going to just display this. But if
there are search results then it's going
to display this partial which is for
each individual search result. So um
that
is each of these you know each one of
these is powered by this search result
partial. Let's take a look at that. And
there's actually quite a bit of um
customization that you can build right
into this. So, for example, let's say I
wanted to display an icon with each of
these. Um I could do that. If I go back
into the search result, I can add
icon name and let's just use the book
icon.
And so now I'm going to search again.
And so now we have a little icon there.
So that's kind of cool. Um we also have
options for like if you're searching for
users and each user has an avatar. Of
course we have an avatars component. You
might want to show like the user's name
and their avatar um in the search
results. So you can do all that using
any of these customization options that
we give you um built into this search
result uh partial. So for now we're
going to keep it simple. We're going to
get rid of that icon and we're just
going to display the title and even the
description is optional. You can you can
get rid of that. But um again our
generator automatically inserted the
title column which we said like use the
column named title and we said we
specified that we want to use the
excerpt. Um so result here represents a
post right. So the results each result
we want to look at the the excerpt and
then remember that weird thing where we
defined the
um the the link path and I only typed in
post path well our generator grabbed
that and then it added its own uh
parenthesis here to to build out you
know it's because it's within this each
loop that's why we had to do that that
weird system. I might improve that in
the future but that's how we did it. If
your postpath link ends up being
incorrect, if it throws an error, then
you want to come into this file, this
search.turbbor erb, and just fix that up
and then you'll be good to go. Oh yeah,
one more thing and that is the uh
navigation of the search results. So if
I open this again and I get some search
results again, I can use my arrow keys
down and up to go through these and or
come right back to the field. And all of
that is handled again in our stimulus
controller. We're going to kind of come
full circle here. You can see navigate
results. So that's looking for um arrow
down or arrow up key events and then um
and then it's going to sort of like
cycle through each of the search results
and it has some logic in there to make
sure like if we're at the end, you know,
don't keep going and and that sort of
thing. So all of that is handled. You
get it all right out of the box when you
install the search component from
instrumental components. And if you have
any questions about this or any
questions about building with Rails or
with AI or with components, uh, leave
them in the comments. I would love to do
more videos on how to build Rails apps
with AI and cursor. And yeah, thanks for
watching. See you.